<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of Dr. Still.'s late book against the Church of Rome together with a short postil upon his text.</title>
            <author>J. V. C. (John Vincent Canes), d. 1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18260</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12601542</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12601542</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33124)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 347:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of Dr. Still.'s late book against the Church of Rome together with a short postil upon his text.</title>
                  <author>J. V. C. (John Vincent Canes), d. 1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 64 [i.e. 76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An answer to Stillingfleet's A discourse concerning the idolatry practised in the Church of Rome.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Discourse concerning the idolatry practised in the Church of Rome.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64186:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF Dr. <hi>Still</hi>'s late BOOK AGAINST <hi>The Church of</hi> ROME. Together With a ſhort Poſtil upon His TEXT.</p>
            <q>Non omnia ſunt quae videntur, nec videntur omnia quae ſunt.</q>
            <p>1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64186:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64186:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ΤΩ ΚΑΘΟΛΙΚΩ <hi>Stillingfleeton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Book, Sir, which taken up with better affairs, you ſent unto me, that I might, after I had read it over, draw an Abridgment of it for you, with my own thoughts ſuper-added in the cloſe, by way of a ſhort Comment thereon, is the ſecond production, as it ſeems, of Doctor <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> againſt Popery. Leſs diſpleaſing it is I think to a Reader, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo tireſome, as ſome other Books which have iſſued forth on that Side againſt the ways of Catholick Religion. For there is ſome Truth in his Citations, a ſeaſoning of Salt and comical Wittineſs ſprinkled all over; and no ſuch thick groſs venom of maliciouſneſs, wherewith other Books of that kind are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>harged, appearing, though much of it lie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id, throughout his Book. Indeed he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erts all things by his various ſubtilty: But that is no more, but what his own ſame and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64186:3"/>intereſt, here principally aimed at, would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uire. And we muſt give him leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide alſo, and play and ſport himſelf in his Book, as a Leviathan in his own waters. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s his paſtime and pleaſure, and a ſweetneſs qſteemed perhaps neceſſary to his life. And who would be ſo ill-natur'd as to envy it him? Beſides, it is a pretty piece of Rhetorick, both fit and very efficacious to create in his Proteſtant Readers an opinion of his uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring confidence, which is the one great end of his Labours. And if we be thus kind, he will in recompence of that our civility, give leave I ſuppoſe to Catholicks, who ſee him ſo jocund and ſupinely careleſs in his errours, thence to conclude the ſtrange inconſiderate ſecurity of the merry man.</p>
            <p>But we muſt know, Sir, that this his elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Book againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as he ſpeaks, although it be his ſecond, yet is it not intended to be his laſt: For, <hi>If Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks have any thing to ſay,</hi> quoth he, <hi>either againſt our Church, or in defence of their own, let them come into the open Field, from when<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they have of late ſo wiſely withdrawn themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> finding ſo little ſucceſs in it.</hi> Thus he ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in his Preface, threatning (if I underſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> him right) another Knocker, as ſtout a o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> as this can be, if any one dare to appear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt him, or ſay ſo much as <hi>Boh</hi> to a Goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64186:3"/>And theſe words of his, import I think a Challenge, called commonly a Defiance; which Catholicks as ſoon as they had read, thought it as much their duty, as it ſounded to be the Doctors deſire, to fit their Slings unto their Arms, and meet him. But the thing proved alas to be but a Copy of the Doctors Countenance, quite differing from his heart. For the Preſſes, guarded enough before againſt Catholicks, was preſently within a month after his Book came forth, ſo ſtoutly beſet, ſo frequently invaded, ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſearched night and day, eſpecially by the induſtry of one of them, who entring into the Printing-houſes, cried out aloud, <hi>And what! have ye here any thing againſt the Doctor Stillingfleet? hah!</hi> that what before was difficil, and extreamly dangerous, was now become impoſſible. So that I believe no Catholick in <hi>England</hi> can do him the favour which the Doctor thirſts after ſo earneſtly in his Lips. He challenged the Papiſts for his Credit, and ſtopt up their way for his Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: He would firſt make the world believe they cannot anſwer him, and then provides that they ſhall not. This ſeems to be his mind.</p>
            <p>And yet I think, Sir, there be few Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Gentlemen in <hi>England</hi> who deſire not as earneſtly as any Catholick, to ſee ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64186:4"/>to his Book: So little do they think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves concerned in a Scroll which neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends their Religion, nor hurts or touches ours; wherein nothing is ſaid, but what might as well be ſpoken by a <hi>Mahometan, Jew,</hi> or <hi>Pagan;</hi> and the moſt part of that which is put to diſable Catholick Religion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes Chriſtianity it ſelf. Some of them offered themſelves to print a Reply for us: But they offered but words. For they found that the Biſhop durſt not give a Licenſe to any of our Catholick Books, onely ſo far as to ſecure the Printer from danger; although the Doctor be a Foe to their Rank and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Catholick Religion a Friend. This is, truly Sir, a very ſad caſe, that they can free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give one a Licenſe to defame men, and yet dare not give others a Licenſe to clear themſelves. Doctor <hi>Couſins</hi> when he was in <hi>Paris,</hi> ſpake up and down ſo freely againſt Catholick Religion, that their Clergy hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, came to him, and told him plainly, <hi>That if he had ought to ſay againſt their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they would both get him a Licenſe from the Biſhop to print his Book<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and themſelves pay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whole charges, and then anſwer him when they had done, for his ſatisfaction.</hi> But we poor Creatures can obtaint no favour in our own Countrey, no leave to ſpeak or juſtifie our ſelves, no Licenſe to print a Book for our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64186:4"/>defence, when we are both ſcurrilouſly libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and falſely ſlandered, and imperiouſly challenged to anſwer: Nor is there any open field for our poor men to come forth into, that I know of, but <hi>Tybourn;</hi> and that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Doctors meaning. It does mightily amaze our Catholicks all over the Land, to have their ears thus beaten with ſlanders, which are both of a high nature, and ſtill notoriouſly falſe, year by year, without any end; thereby to make us odious to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and them to God. Our bleſſed Lord have pity on us; and either open, if it may be thy will, our Magiſtrates hearts towards us, or ſtop the Miniſters mouths againſt us; that our good Name and Peace may return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy great Glory. We are, if we be ſilent, proclaimed guilty; and if we ſpeak, inſolent. What can we do, Sir, here, but ſtill commend our ſelves unto our heavenly Lord, who mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly preſerves us. We do either ſubſiſt after this life, or not. Our Proteſtant Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men muſt needs believe one of theſe two things: Either ſome Religion is true, or it is all a fiction. If it be all a fiction, and there is no life to come, then are they as guilty as we; nay ſomething more; for they have taken away our Churches from us, for themſelves to diſſemble in. If there be a life to come, and this everlaſting, then can there
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64186:5"/>certainly be nothing of greater importance in this world, than to know, when many ways are pretended to it, which of them is the moſt authentick and trueſt, wherein we may be both happy and ſafe for ever. Why then are we, who are the firſt, not permitted to ſpeak, while all others are permitted to blaſpheme us? If we prove to go amiſs, the danger is our own: and if we be in the right, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be any danger unto them to know it. All the poſitive things of Religion which any of them do keep, they have them all from us, we borrow nothing from them. And the nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive points which ſeparate them from us, ſeem to us as falſe and impious, as they can poſſibly appear true to them. They have as many Articles to believe as we, onely ſome of them which made the ſeparation are affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to us, and negative to them: And one Affirmers word is to be taken in Judgment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ten Deniers. And yet will they neither read our Books, nor ſuffer us to print any, when we are falſified, and miſ-interpreted, and challenged and obliged to do it, for fear I think our Religion ſhould prove true. All rejoyce when a Book is written againſt Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: but no man ſeeks to be informed. They will have it by all means to be eſteemed falſe, be it in it ſelf what it will or can be. And in that ſtrange prejudice men venture to die,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64186:5"/>onely for the pleaſure of a Miniſter and his VVife and Children, who muſt needs have it ſo.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this his preſent book, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the Idolatry,</hi> &amp;c. was, it ſeems, a queſtion or two propunded unto Mr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> by I know not what Gentlewoman, who having heard the Doctor ſay, That <hi>Proteſtants if they turned Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, would loſe their Salvation;</hi> told him, That if Proteſtants ſay ſo, then are they full as uncharitable as Papiſts themſelves, who aver the like of Proteſtants: She therefore conſults ſome Catholick Gentleman in the buſineſs; I do not know whom neither. But he, it ſeems, put into her hand two queſtions, to ſhow to Doctor <hi>Still.</hi> in her next encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Firſt was, <hi>Whether the ſame motives which ſecured one born and bred in the Catholick Church to continue in it, might not alſo ſerve to ſecure a Proteſtant, who convinced by thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives ſhould embrace it.</hi> The ſecond was, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſuffice to be a Chriſtian in genere, or it be alſo neceſſary to adjoyn to ſome Church of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in particular?</hi> Theſe be the two que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of theſe two queſtions the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor reſolves affirmatively; <hi>I affirm,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that a Chriſtian by vertue of his being ſo, is bound to joyn to the Communion of ſome Church
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64186:6"/>or Congregation in particular.</hi> Thus he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves it, and ſpeaks not a word more of that buſineſs. Yet here we may take notice that the ſaid Reſolution of his, is quite contrary both to a book of his called <hi>Irenicon,</hi> written in the times of our late Anarchy, and alſo to his firſt work written more lately againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery. For all the whole ſcope of both theſe books, is to ſhow that a Chriſtian by vertue of his being ſo, is not bound to joyn in the Communion of any one Church in particular, or any Organical Body, as he calls it. And that becauſe every ſuch body, either that is or has been in the world, is liable to errour, falſhood, and corruptions. And what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity indeed can there be in me to joyn in any Communion, which may go aſtray and miſlead me, ſince I cannot do worſe if I remain free and all alone, and may perhaps do better? But theſe contradictions are ſmall matters. So long as the Doctor oppoſes the Catholick Church, out of which they are all fallen, he is a Proteſtant good enough, whatever he hold in particular, either contrary to himſelf or any others.</p>
            <p>The firſt queſtion, which is the occaſion and ſubject of this his preſent book: he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves negatively; averring, <hi>that the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives which might ſecure one born and bred in the Catholick Church to continue in it, cannot ſecure
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64186:6"/>a Proteſtant, convinced by them to imbrace it.</hi> And this his Aſſertion he diſcourſes at large, and confirms by various Syllogiſmes; becauſe invincible hinderance may perhaps excuſe the one, but not the other; becauſe the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant is ſafe in his own Church, and therefore has no neceſſity to leave it: becauſe there is imminent danger in the Roman Church; where there is ſo much Idolatry, ſo many hinderances of good life and devotion, ſo much diviſions; ſo much uncertainty of faith in it. Unto theſe reſolutions and argumentations of his, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Propoſer adjoyned preſently his own reply, a very rational me thinks and good one. Hereupon the Doctor wrote and ſet forth this his preſent book, called <hi>A Diſcourſe againſt the Idolatry, &amp;c.</hi> both to inlarge his own argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to diſable the Catholick Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Reply. And this was the occaſion, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and ſubject of the book you put in my hand to peruſe, and write to you the ſubſtance of it with ſome few brief thoughts of my own upon it,</p>
            <p>Indeed the whole book is a kind of Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick Act or Commencement: ſuch a one as we have once a year in our famous <hi>Oxford</hi> &amp; <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> written and printed for peoples de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and paſtime; and if ſo it pleaſe the Stars, for his own honour and preferment by our Doctor. And it came forth very ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64186:7"/>about a fortnight before the <hi>Oxford;</hi> Act, to ſave the wits living here abouts, the great charges and ſome kind of pains of a Journey thither, being now furniſhed well enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand with as ſubtile and good an Act, as that may haply be, at our own Doors, and which may pleaſe the women ſomewhat better, in our mother tongue.</p>
            <p>The concluſions defended in this <hi>Holborn</hi> Act are theſe three.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Popery is idolatrous.</hi> And this is accompliſhed in two of his poſitions which he calls Chapters.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Popery is a hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to a good life and devotion.</hi> And this is diſpatched at one other breathing, named his third Chapter.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Popery is divided and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united in it ſelf.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
And this puſt out in his fifth Chapter, which concludes his book, And in midſt of this great Act, riſes up a prevaricating <hi>Tripos,</hi> to refreſh our weariſomeneſs, and make a little ſport. And he takes up the whole Scene of his fourth Chapter. And his Theme is, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſcime: the Church of</hi> Romes <hi>Fanatiſciſme;</hi> or the <hi>Fanaticiſm of the Roman Church.</hi> And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my word, it has made many people merry, not the ſofter ſex only, but the rougher and more ſerious mankind. And all do ſo clap and commend the man, that one may well believe he has received his reward; Idolatry, ill life and diviſions of the Roman Church, which are his three leſs wild concluſions, we have in part al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64186:7"/>heard of; even as we have heard talk of <hi>Europe, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa.</hi> But <hi>Fanaticiſme,</hi> his merriment is, <hi>I</hi> think, the proper and peculair diſcovery of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> himſelf: And he may deſerve either to give or take a ſirname from it; as <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> took from <hi>Africa,</hi> and <hi>Veſputius Americus</hi> gave to <hi>America</hi> his new found Land. What is it, that wit and induſtry cannot bring to light, if they be joyntly bent both of them upon the ſearch? And a new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery eſpecially of a rich pleaſant Country full of curioſities is ſo pleaſant to the Diſcoverer himſelf, ſo naturally pleaſant that <hi>I</hi> cannot but think that Doctor <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> at his invention of <hi>Fanaticiſme,</hi> wherewith he hoped to make many others merry, laughed heartily himſelf.</p>
            <p>He begins his Book with the Roman Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: and he does wiſely in it. For Idolatry is ſuch a terrible thundering charge; that in all Readers judgments that Church is half condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned already, which hath that crime ſo much as laid upon it. Men therefore chooſe rather to be accounted Atheiſts than Idolaters. For the firſt argues wit, the other ſtupidity. Nor will one man of a hundred trouble himſelf to read over a book written on any purpoſe of clearing from that enormous crime either himſelf or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion profeſſed by the Author of it. Be the imputation never ſo falſe, yet is it ſtill a blaſting imputation; which kills and overthrows, not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64186:8"/>ſo much by proving as by naming it. He muſt needs be impious who is an Idolater; and he muſt be an Idolater who is called ſo. Be it never ſo unjuſt, it is ſtill a witty trick to cry out againſt him as an Idolater, whoſe honour and livelihood we would here in <hi>England</hi> undermine. Sad experience has proved this to be true too too often. And the Great God of Heavens anger lyes <hi>I</hi> fear heavily upon us for it. This thus far. Now forward,</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IMAGE-IDOLATRY.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Church of Rome worſhips God by I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and is therefore guilty of Idolatry by giving to the Creature the worſhip due only to the Creator. For God having forbidden any ſuch ſort of worſhiping him by his own law and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments given by Moſes, wherein he forbids his people to make any kind of image,</hi> peſel the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munah, eikon glypton, ſculptile, <hi>any thing repreſented either by carving toole or penſil, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not own that worſhip, nor can any ſuch worſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> terminate upon God. And the reaſon of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> law of Moſes is unchangeable, which is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> God's infinite and incomprehenſible Deity cann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be repreſented. For which reaſon the wiſeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Heathen both particular men and Natio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> judged all ſuch repreſentations of the inviſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64186:8"/>Godhead to be incongruous and unbecoming his glory; And if this were inconſiſtent with Gods nature and will in the old Law much more in the new, where we are taught to worſhip God in ſpirit and truth, and to have no low unworthy thought of God. It might therefore ſeem more rational to worſhip God in the Sun and Moon which have more of God in them, and to ſay our prayers to the Sun and Moon then to any image or ſhadow; the ſame argument which excuſes the one will juſtifie the other much more. For this reaſon St. Paul teaches that the Godhead is not like to gold or ſilver or ſtone, and blames thoſe who change the glory of the incorruptible God into the image of corruptible man. And the Heathens in doing this did ill: although the wiſer ſort among them teſtifie that they did not hold their ſtatues to be Gods, but that they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped God in them. And yet ſome antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers diſputed notwithſtanding againſt that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then practice and counted it idolatry. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Germanus <hi>Patriark of</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>ſayes expreſly that Chriſtians make no repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the inviſible Deity; and</hi> Damaſcene <hi>that it is madneſs to go about it. Wherefore the Synode of</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>and that of</hi> Frankford <hi>pleaded hard againſt the making of any images amongſt Chriſtians however the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Council of</hi> Nice <hi>vainly went about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them as innocent and uſeful helps. Finally,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64186:9"/>Moſes himſelf explicates by his deeds the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own Law when he was ſo highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with Aaron for the golden Calf he had made the people in his abſence. And yet Aaron did not make it to bring the people into heathen idolatry, but to give them only a Symbole of the Angel who was to go before the people: As alſo the two calves ſet up by Jeroboam in Dan and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel were ſet up only to keep the people from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to Jeruſalem, and not to bring them to the idolatry of heathens. And therefore Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians never uſed any images, as the learned of the Church of Rome acknowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 1. This is the ſum of the Doctors Diſcourſe in this his firſt Chapter. And he cannot but expect his Reader ſhould have a mighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of either his moſt high or moſt deep Divinity, who hath converſt ſo much with the learned fort of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the graver ſort of Philoſophers, and wiſer ſort of Heathens. Nothing does he here deliver, that was ſo much as thought of by the common ſort, the vulgar ſort, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſort of Mankind. And O what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and content of heart will it be unto him, if he could meet with an adverſary of his <hi>learned ſort</hi> too, who viewing his airy ſubtilties ſhould oppoſe him ſeriouſly, as if he were ſerious himſelf; and then diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh as if he were dealing with ſome ſolid
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64186:9"/>Divine; and then ply him with proofs and teſtimonies, refell him by ſhorter enthymems and longer ſyllogiſmes; ſubtilly ſearch in what Mood and figure he ſpeaks; and then tell him how his conſequence flaggs, or ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent is ambiguous, till he have learendly conſumed a hundred pages in refutation of a trifle. Then ſurely will the Doctor be judged by all parties to be as he would be thought to be, an able man.</p>
               <p>§ 2. The Catholick Chruch uſes indeed both in their publick and private oratories, ſome pious repreſentations of our holy Lord, either in his paſſion, or birth, reſurrection, or aſcention, or miraculous working of ſome divine miracle: And theſe holy figures of his are accompanied commonly with ſome others of his bleſſed Virgin Mother, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Apoſtles, valorous Martyrs, holy Confeſſors, chaſt Virgins, or other happy followers of our Lord, who through many tribulations and a conſtant exerciſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vertues have paſſed hence to a bleſſed life. All which do mightily avail, unto our retiredneſs and recollection; when we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the houſe of prayer, a holy place ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated and ſanctified for Gods ſervice, from our own houſes or the ſtreets. And the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect or eſteem we have for ſuch figures, is nothing but what we bear either unto the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64186:10"/>hiſtories recorded of the ſame perſons or to thoſe good rules of life and promiſes of Goſpel, which thoſe Worthies have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, for the incouragement and imitation of us, who are now ſtrugling in that wicked world, which they overcame before us. For example, as we reverence the hiſtory of Chriſts incarnation, ſounding in our ear; ſo do we look upon the figure of it repreſented to our eye: As we love the ſtory of St. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalens converſion; ſo do we like her picture. As we honour St. Pauls life and martyrdome; ſo do we reſpect his image. And St. Lawrences moſt cruel paſſion upon the hot burning Gridiron, when it is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to us in a picture, we are in the ſelf ſame manner affected towards it, as we are to the invincible vertue and patience there ſhown for the Love and honour of Jeſus our Lord, whoſe ſteps he followed. So that, what authentick hiſtory records to us in words, of the vertue and valour of any of our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Anceſtors; or what holy Goſpel tells us, of the glory and crown to be rendred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the good works of ſobriety, charity, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, purity, patience, and the like: the ſame is without words painted unto us by theſe compendious hieroglyphicks, ſerving more ſpeedily then words can do, to faſten us unto a ſtrict recollection in our prayers
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64186:10"/>by one ſhort glance about us; and to a fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and awfulneſs of Gods preſence in that place where we are met together for his Service, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the figures of ſo many of our pious Anceſtours who are gone to Heaven before us; and alſo to a diſſipation of any worldly thoughts, that may, as they are apt enough to do, at that time come along with us there unto our hinderance. All this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit we have by our Pictures, when we have haply no book to look upon, or know not by our ignorance to read, or cannot by darkneſs or other lettance attend unto that labour. And this is all the whole buſineſs of Images, as to Religion. In the Road of Philoſophy trodden by School-Divines, where thouſands of concluſions over and above faith are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced and oppoſed by one another unto the ſharpning of their wits, many things are ſaid about every thing, as the creation, reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thè like, which faith in the ſame things is ſilent of; Nor are we in our defence of faith concerned at all in them. And it may be esſily diſcerned by our Catholick practice. what uſe we make of our Images, when of a hundred people entring into a Church, not one of them ever caſts his eye wiſtly upon them, but contented with a general glance, compoſe themſelves preſently unto their prayers and meditations they keep ſilently in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64186:11"/>ſpirit towards God. And when our pictures are ſo ſullied and ſpoiled, that they will no more ſerve our uſe, we put them into the fire, as we would do alſo a page of ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures utterly obliterated and fouled.</p>
               <p>§. 3. Indeed all the whole buſineſs of the uſe of Images at all, is but a matter of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and government, for the help of people in the great work of recollection and prayer; as is the uſe of Churches, and the muſick uſed in them, with the harp, viol, and other inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the uſe of beads and prayer-books. All which our Religion could ſpare, and yet be not at all impaired, as to any its eſſential or ſubſtantial parts. Nay there inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences in any one of theſe things. Nor do I know any good thing in this world without ſome inconvenience or other. It is enough for us that the conveniences and benefits of any good we have or uſe, are more and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the inconveniences be. Many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Prelates in Chriſtianity have at times ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted very ſtrongly againſt Organs, as ſome hindrance of the great work of ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation which Chriſtian people meet to, practice together in their holy aſſemblies, the great paramount work of Chriſtianity, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at Maſs. But theſe men, although mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unto that their exception by a Zeal not evil, yet were they fain to yield at laſt unto
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64186:11"/>the prevailing reaſons of other Prelates which overbore their leſſer ones. Some other of our Catholick Doctors and Prelates would have had us to have uſed no pictures; that Jews and Pagans might not catch at that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to cavil againſt our Chriſtianity as they did. But all theſe ſubmitted at laſt, unto the prevailing part; by whom they were made to underſtand that the inconveniences they ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged were but imaginary and ſmall, the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences great and real. There have been not a few who have excepted againſt much vocal prayer; becauſe it took up too much of the time which would be better employed in the more principal work of prayer in ſpirit. But yet could they not carry it, although their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were very plauſible aad good; becauſe that high and Angelical prayer in ſpirit, agreed not equally to all men, or to any one conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of fleſh and blood equally at all times and places, as vocal prayer does. Some have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked even our material Temples, built up ſo ſumptuouſly as they are; becauſe God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe and incomprehenſible, dwells not in buildings made by mans hands; Heaven is his Seat, and Earth his Footſtool; Yet could they not obtain, that our Churches ſhould be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pulled down, or not built up. Prayer-books were nothing at all in uſe amongſt Chriſtians in primitive times; when they pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64186:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>almoſt altogether in ſpirit, and uſed no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vocal prayer but that our Lord taught us. And yet this hinders us not, either to make ſuch books or uſe them in following times. Inſtead of our beads in wood or mettal, they uſed in ancient times a bag of little ſtones, by the emptying whereof they knew that they had ſaid over our Lords prayer a hundred or perhaps three hundred times, according as any one in his devotion had prefixed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf every day of his life to do for Gods glory and ſervice. And there might be inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences pretended againſt our preſent beads, eſpecially thoſe of gold and pearl. But they will not be thrown away for that. Our Church-muſick has been more than once op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and that by Prelates moſt holy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned men, who deemed it an unſufferable lettance to the ſpiritual recollection which Chriſtians ought above all things to attend unto, that they may have our Lords good Spirit, and his holy operations in them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they meet together at their holy Synaxis. But Church-muſick is kept up to this day, notwithſtanding their reaſon againſt it, which is very good, for other reaſons no. leſs good and great than it; ſpecified and ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the far greater number of pious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates for it. And yet if all or the greater part of Catholick Prelates meeting together
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64186:12"/>ſhould take away all theſe outward helps from us, beads and books, ſinging and Church-mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, pictures, and Churches, and all, finding the inconveniences to be now greater than they have been, and weightier than any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience we have by them: though the thing would ſeem very ſtrange to us, yet ought we I think to obey them reſignedly, and attend wholly unto our ſpiritual mediations, either alone, or in our Euchariſtian meetings, and to the other good works commanded or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled us in Goſpel in expectation of our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bliſs and eternal happineſs in God, which can never be taken from us: though all things of diſcipline or helps in government be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>§ 4. And now it is time to turn back and view the ſubject of this Chapter; that we may ſee if any one period in it be true and pertinent. He tells us firſt, that Papiſts <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God by Images,</hi> which logically is not true; Then <hi>that a repreſentation of the inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deity cannot be made;</hi> which is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; Then <hi>that the worſhip given to God by an image does not terminate upon God:</hi> which is neither pertinent nor true. And ſo he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds on to the very end of his Chapter, with ſounds either empty or falſe, or both; neither heeding or caring what he ſays, ſo he do but mention learned papiſts, and wiſer heathens,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64186:13"/>which may help to butterreſs up his reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I cannot but remember here, the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow or Ghoſt in Virgil which Juno made of Aeneas, to draw her beloved Turnus out of the field; It ſeemed to fight and threaten, and preſs on and give back. But nothing at all was done really.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Tum dea nube cavâ tenuem ſine viribus umbram.</l>
                  <l>In faciem Aeneae, viſu mirabile monſtrum,</l>
                  <l>Dardaniis ornat telis, clypeum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> jubaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Divini aſſimilat capitis, dat inania verba.</l>
                  <l>Dat ſine mente ſonum greſſuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> effingit euntis</l>
                  <l>Morte obitâ quales fama eſt volitare figuras</l>
                  <l>Aut quae ſopitos deludunt ſomnia ſenſûs.</l>
                  <l>Ac primas laeta ante acies exultat imago</l>
                  <l>Irritat<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> virum telis ac voce laceſſit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And ſuch a ſhadow of controverſie is all this preſent Chapter, and his whole book alſo: a foming face and feeble force: big but empty words: rumbling and yet inſignificant ſounds: quick profers, and no progreſs: a daring ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow or armed Ghoſt, without either body or bones. And yet ſuch a thing as defies the whole Catholick Church; ſteps out from the reſt of his Camp and defies them all alone defies them both in letters ſyllables and words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this is all. For he touches no body. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Catholicks by the advice and allowance
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64186:13"/>of their Prelates do keep amongſt them the repreſentation of the divine Founder of their Religion, who appeared amongſt us by his unſpeakable Love in form of a Man; and of ſome of his holy followers in the way he chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out for us; therefore he talks of Moloch and Milcom, Oſiris and Iſis, Chemoſh and Aſtaroth, Baal Peor and Rimmon, golden Bulls and Remphan, the calves of Dan and Bethel. And what is all this for? Wy to over-run Papiſts, and beat us down; How can it do that? Theſe idols were ſet up by heathens in oppoſition to the true God, and in the very place of God, as darkneſs in the night time is in the place of light. This is true, what then? and therefore I muſt not forſooth keep the figure of Jeſus Chriſt or of St. Paul or other domeſtick of my own religion for my own incouragement therein. What likeneſs, what conſequence is there in all this? Which is Remphan and where is Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loch? Which is the Calf and where is the Bull? Nay and here it is worth our obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving too, that Proteſtant Gentlemen and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of England, Miniſters and Biſhops too, have all pictures in their Chambers as well as Catholicks; even thoſe of our holy Apoſtles and Martyrs as well as others. And there they are good and lawful figures; but in our Chambers they are Bulls of Baſan, and Calves
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64186:14"/>of Bethel among us. Catholick pictures are againſt Moſes his Law; but theirs are not ſo; Although they be repreſentations both in Heaven above and Earth below, and Waters under earth, expreſſy by the ſame Law forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; for example Moon and Stars, Dogs and Cats, Whales and Dolphins. The picture of Martin Luther in their Chamber is the lawful effigies of a man. But Saint Stephen in our Cloſet is a Calf. Can any man who talks at this rate, be thought to be one that has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed either with the learned ſort of Papiſts or the wiſer ſort of Heathens: or one ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that had never any converſation at all ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with reaſon or men. <hi>O but Catholicks worſhip God by their images, which Proteſtants do not.</hi> I marry, this is a huge fault indeed, that Catholicks take thereby occaſion to think of God and his manifold mercies, and bleſs his name, and truſt in him. For they no other way worſhip God by Images: This is the mortal ſin which Catholicks commit. And if that illogical ſpeech of the Doctor, <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks worſhip God by Images,</hi> be drawn into any kind of ſence, it can be no other than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that Catholicks take occaſion by the pious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Martyrs to think of Gods mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold graces and mercies towards them, and thereupon truſt in him afreſh, and bleſs his name: which great errour the Doctor, it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64186:14"/>ſeems, does carefully avoid. The ancient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut Chriſtians thought of God and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him by any thing, any good thing they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed; the verdant fields and ſweet flowers, comfortable air, and pleaſing light, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, valleys and liquid ſtreams; Plumbs, Pears, Apples, and chearful Grapes; by the vertue, charity and devotion of men, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of Angels, &amp;c. But now we muſt take heed of that. We may taſte a Plumb or a Cherry, we may eat a veniſon Paſty and drink good wine if we can get it; nay we may have fine pictures in our Chambers, even the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Jeſus Chriſt crucified, or any of his followers: we may have all this, if we be ſuch good Proteſtants as Mr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> and never think of God, or <hi>worſhip God</hi> by it. But if we worſhip God by it, if we think of God by it, then it is all poiſon to us. All is ſuddenly turned to Moloch, to Remphan, to Baal Peor, to Aſhtaroth, to Aarons golden Steer and the Calves of Bethel. If we do but eat a cuſtard thinking of God, or <hi>worſhipping God by it,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently it becomes a <hi>Remphan</hi> or Chiun, the idol of the Arabians. Walking upon Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead-hill, as people uſe innocently enough to do, if caſting our eyes about the proſpect we think of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by it, as Catholicks are wont, the hill before innocent is now become a <hi>Baal Peor</hi> the idol of the Moabites. A Citizen
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64186:15"/>walking to the Tower, may look harmleſly enough upon the Crown and royal. Robes there. But he muſt take heed then, that he fall not into a meditation of Heaven, or the glory of its great King, to worſhip him in his heart by it. For then it becomes to him an <hi>Adramelech,</hi> the idol of Sepharvaim. And he muſt beware of the like abuſe when he ſees the Chamber and Table where his Majeſty ſits in Council with his Peers, leſt it become a <hi>Moloch</hi> to him, the idol of the Moabites. The very Flags and Banners often ſeen in London-ſtreets, make ſome ſimple ſoul to think of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem above, the peace and happy company there, and the God of all: but then O how ſuddenly is the Streamer metamorphoſed and turned into <hi>Neſroch,</hi> the idol of Senacherib. Some are ſo bold, when they either ſee or hear of any corrupted by the French-pox and lechery, to thank God who has preſerved them, and <hi>worſhip God by it.</hi> And thereby ſin no leſs grievouſly than Maacham the Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her of Aſa King of Judah in worſhipping her idol Priap or <hi>Nimphleſeth.</hi> A gentleman cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon God not in words onely, but very heartily, when a troubleſome Fly got into his Eye, and much afflicted him: but he little thought that by that piety of his he had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as deeply as they that worſhip <hi>Baalzebu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the idol of Acaron. Nothing is more ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64186:15"/>with Country Gentlemen, when walking abroad they behold a goodly fair flock of ſheep in paſture of their own, than to thank God and <hi>worſhip God by it;</hi> but little do they think good men, they are guilty of Idolatry thereby, as much guilty as they that worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> the idol of the Philiſtins. Nay a very cow or calf in the meadows, if we take occaſion by it to thank God for his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, or to <hi>worſhip God by it,</hi> is the ſame thing then, as Aarons <hi>Moulten heifer</hi> or Jeroboams <hi>calves</hi> ſet up in Dan and Bethel. And as it is for ſubſtance, ſo for the figures of things. St. Pauls picture ſo long as we do not think of God by it, is a lawful picture. But if we come once to think of God, to <hi>worſhip God by it,</hi> O then that is a Calf too, Aarons Calf, one of Jeroboams Calves, &amp;c. This think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, this worſhipping of God by any thing, this is the peſtilential blaſt, that ſpoils all. It turns ſweet into bitter, lawful into unlawful, things innocent into ſin, and good things to death. The repreſentation of our bleſſed Lord crucified for us, ſo long as we think not of him may paſs for a good innocent or at leaſt indifferent thing; but if we once think ſeriouſly of him, if we worſhip God by it, then, O Mr. Stillingfleet, what is it then? And yet anſwer me not. For I will not have thoſe blaſphemous words here repeated.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64186:16"/>Speak them to a Jew in order to Jeſus Chriſt and he will embrace and love you. But a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cannot endure to hear them.</p>
               <p>§ 5. <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſaith he <hi>worſhip God by images, and ſo are guilty of idolatry,</hi> Catholicks may hear this, but can never underſtand what he means. They are never taught in any of their Catechiſms to worſhip God by Images. None of their ſpiritual books wherein all religious Duties are importunately urged and preſſed upon them ever mention it: and their practice does not infer it. For if it did, they would eaſilieſt underſtand it who beſt know what themſelves do. They are taught, and do in their practice endeavour to worſhip God in their heart and ſoul; and ardent affections ſtreaming forth thence towards him. They worſhip him with bended knees, lips and voice, hearts and eyes l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fted up unto him. They worſhip him with the aſſiſtance of Gods good Spirit, the Prieſts Sacrifice, and help of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual prayers. They worſhip him by mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſenſuality and carnal appetites, by giving alms and relieving the poor and needy for his Love, by obſerving his Laws and Counſels, by reſigning to his good will and pleaſure in all things, eſpecially in time of afflicting perſecutions, when they ſuffer all manner of reproach, lies and calumnies, loſs of goods and ſometimes life it ſelf for his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64186:16"/>name ſake patiently. They worſhip him in Cloſets, in Church-aſſemblies, in the fields, as they are walling, on Land or Sea, where they have opportunity to do it. Thus doth their religion teach them to worſhip God, as with the right cauſes and inſtruments; as by the true effects and operations; as in the times and places ſeaſonable for worſhip and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But how they ſhould <hi>worſhip God by images,</hi> or (as he ſpeaketh oftner in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of his diſcourſe) <hi>in images;</hi> this they do not eaſily underſtand. When he lays any thing to Catholicks charge, he ought to ſpeak I ſhould think as Catholicks do, and then he will be underſtood by them. It is not to be conceived how any one can worſhip God <hi>by images,</hi> and <hi>in images,</hi> but either for the real preſence there; or ideal imitation; or ſome ſort of occaſion of worſhip ariſing thence. And ſo God muſt be worſhipped by them and in them, either preſentially, ideally, or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally. And it cannot be preſentially. For ſo God is no otherwiſe preſent in a picture than in the wall it hangs upon: nor yet ideally; for the picture for example of St. Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen or St. Paul, is no idea of that inviſible and glorious Godhead; nor yet is any other, as the Crucifix for example or Chriſt our Lord in his Birth or Reſurrection; for all theſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures are repreſentations of his humanity, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64186:17"/>no idea's of his Deity at all. And Mr. Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet muſt needs mean one of theſe two ways. For otherwiſe he could not charge them with idolatry for it. And therefore I ſay that his charge is falſe and ſlanderous. But if he mean that they worſhip God by images and in their images, occaſionally; which is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral interpretation and the only true one: Then is ſuch a work ſo far from Idolatry, that it is a ſublime piety. For what can they better do, then to give God thanks for ſo great graces, mercies, helps, and comforts beſtowed in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord upon his Apoſtles. Martyrs, Confeſſors, and Virgins, when they look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their figures and pictures either in their contemplations, or patience of Martyrdome, or converſion of the world, ſubduing and bringing fleſh, Satan and the world under their feet: eſpecially if Catholicks conceive thereby ſome pious reſolution, as well they may, of doing ſomething the more and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſuffering for God, in imitation of thoſe pious Heroes our Predeceſſours in religion, and yet naturally but fleſh and blood as we our ſelves are. <hi>I</hi> ſay all this is ſignal piety, and our Chriſtian duty. And according to, this morall meaning Catholicks if they do worſhip God by their im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges and in their images; do well and like good Chriſtians. But the Doctor will not charge them I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64186:17"/>with a matter of ſo much truth and great piety as this is, although his words cannot make out any other ſence that is true, but only this morall one. And the more logical ſence of worſhipping God by images and in images; ideally or preſentially is falſe. Let him even take which ſence he pleaſes, either what juſtifies Catholicks or what ſalſifies his own aſſertion; It is all one to me, whether we ſtand, or he fall.</p>
               <p>§ 6. He adds, <hi>that the worſhip of God by images does not terminate upon God; becauſe God has forbid it and ſo gives Gods honour to the Creature.</hi> This is ſtrange gibberiſh. An act that tends to nothing is no act. If it be ſome act, it tends and has already tended to ſomething; and it terminates upon that thing unto which it tends, and whoſe act it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated. This is clear enough even to a young ſophomore, or one who indeed never yet came into the aire of Philoſophy, if he do but underſtand the terms and words here uſed. For example I cannot ſee a man in the ſtreet, except my viſion terminate upon him; nor can my viſion terminate upon him, but <hi>I</hi> muſt ſee him. And it is all one whether I ſee him cloſe by me, or by my window or in a looking glaſs at home. For I cannot ſee him any way but my ſight muſt terminate upon him, and if it do not, I ſee him not. And
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64186:18"/>this courſe of nature is not hindred, not yet altered at all, becauſe that perſon may haply have forbidden me to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him either this way or that. For our acts or actions are accompliſhed within our ſelves, independently of any acceptance or diſacceptance of them. Acceptance or diſacceptance, commanding or forbidding is another thing, extrinſecal and quite differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the ſubſtance of the act or action. For they ſpecifie onely, either the motive or event which may make the act either good or evil, either grateful or diſpleaſing, but not make it an act or no act, or not to tend where it has tended. And ſo muſt my act of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God by images, terminate upon God, or elſe it is no act of worſhipping God by them; however God may have either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or forbid it. God has forbidden blaſphemy; and yet the act terminates upon him, otherwiſe it could not be a ſin againſt him. And if Gods worſhip by images do not terminate on God, whither on Gods name does it tend; and how is God worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them? This he does not tell us here, unleſs he inſinuate it is thoſe following words of his, <hi>but gives the honour due to God unto the Creature.</hi> But how can that be? If God ſhould have forbid us by his law to ſee a ſtar through a tube; ſhould we not therefore ſee it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64186:18"/>but the tube only, or ſhould not our ſight then be terminated upon the Sar. So it ſeems by this Doctors philoſophy, who hath converſed with the learneder ſort of Papiſts, and the wiſer ſort of heathens, but very little with himſelf. Holy fathers and Doctors have often ſaid, that the honour of an Image re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to the Prototype: but never thought or ſaid, that the honour of the Prototype re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to the image, as it is here affirmed againſt both art and experience. But let us hear him proceed in his diſcourſe. He will ſurely let fall ſome ſence or truth ere long.</p>
               <p>§ 7. <hi>Gods infinite and incomprehenſible Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſaith he, cannot be repreſented.</hi> O here it is. This is very true. What a comfortable thing it is to meet with a draught of truth ſometimes, when a man is dry and thirſts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it. But to what purpoſe is this ſpoken here? Catholicks have no repreſentations of that inviſible Deity, nor none they look after. Figures they have of our Lord Chriſt. born as man amongſt us, and made fleſh, and crucified, and aſcending into Heaven. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures alſo of his holy followers and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs: but repreſentations of the inviſible De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity they never yet ſaw nor heard nor thought of. On then. <hi>The wiſeſt of heathens judged any ſuch repreſentations of the Divine nature incongruous and unbecoming his glory.</hi> Indeed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64186:19"/>they were wiſe heathens, and their judgment very right and good. Nor did I ever hear of any Chriſtian wiſe or unwiſe any otherwiſe minded. O how would this Doctor prevail, if this wiſe Diſcourſe of his, were as perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent as it is true. But he truſts and hopes well, that his good fate will ſo accompany his reader. that he ſhall not doubt at all that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word that is true in his book is alſo to ſome purpoſe. And to ſome purpoſe indeed it is: namely to have it thought, that he is victorious in his maine deſign: although in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and truth it belong nothing at all to it. But let me not ſtop his carreere. <hi>If any ſuch figure of the Deity were inconſiſtent in the old Law, much more in the new where we are commanded to worſhip God in ſpirit and truth.</hi> O uncontrouleable conſequence, ariſing from remiſſes moſt true. No man can or dare deny a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l this. Me thinks I love him here for his reaſon, and cannot but grieve it ſhould be all ſpilt in vain; ſo pure it is and pretious. A little more of this, while he is in a good mood. <hi>It ſeems more rational to worſhip God in the Sun and Moon which have more of God in them then a picture has, and to ſay our prayers to the Sun and Moon then to any Image.</hi> Seems ſo Sir? It is certainly more rational: what ſhould we doubt of? And what a pitty is it, there ſhould be none to be found, who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64186:19"/>God in a picture either ideally or preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially none who ſay their prayers to a picture that this great blow of his might not beat the aire to the indangering of his elbows. Saint <hi>Paul teſtifies that the Godhead is not like either to gold or ſilver or ſtone.</hi> Good St. Paul alwaies ſaid well; and his teſtimony is good at all times; and eſpecially now, when it hits ſo pat with the wiſer heathens. There be many Churches now in England which have ſince our reformation, the Tetragram name of God written upon the walls within ſide in golden letters. Unto thoſe men who did this, it would not ſeem altogether imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, to tell them, that <hi>the Godhead is not like to gold, ſilver or ſtone.</hi> But to ſuch as uſe only the effigies of our Lord according to his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and his holy Apoſtles and Martyrs, what a pitty it is it ſhould be impertinent and wholly loſt. Let him ſpeak on ſome more of his truths. <hi>Germanus Patriark of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople ſaies expreſly that Chriſtians make no repreſentation of the inviſible Deity: and St. Damaſcene affirms it madneſs to go about it.</hi> Marry, God have mercy o'their ſouls for this their expreſs ſaying. Catholicks would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no better a teſtimony for themſelves if they wanted any, then this of thoſe two great Catholick Doctors; that no ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation they have, and none they go
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64186:20"/>about to have. O but he hopes, that all this being true will make ſtrongly againſt the Church of Rome. And will it ſo? I have heard ſay, there be a thouſand Churches in Rome, which are all Churches of Rome equally. Which of them all are concerned in this talk, that their walls may confute him? But he means Catholick people perhaps, oh, O, then all is well, they are ſafe enough and unhurt by all this, which is but their own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and faith. At leaſt he has by theſe fair ſhreds of truth farced up a dozen pages in his book; And he hopes that his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant reader will believe it all to be moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent and appoſite diſcourſe againſt papiſhes, though it be nothing leſs. And if they do ſo think, he has his end, a happy man no doubt.</p>
               <p>§ 8. <hi>Moſes forbad</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the making of any graven thing, and the word which Moſes uſes in that his law for a graven thing is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and ſignifies not an idol only as papiſts ſay, but any picture, likeneſs, image or repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Moſes himſelf ſpeaks, either in heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove or in earth below or waters under the earth, peſel, themurah, eikon glypton, ſculptile, any kind of thing that may be expreſt either with the pencil or graving tool.</hi> Believe me Sir if this be true it will undo all our Painters, who come flocking hither into England as the only thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64186:20"/>place for them out of Holland, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, France and Italy too; and here fill the Land with peſels, themunahs, eikons, glyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, ſculptile's, and any things they can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs with their pencils for our delight; Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins, whales, and other fiſh of the ſea; birds of the Aire, beaſts, flowers, woods gallant men and fair women, all that ever Moſes forbad to be expreſt. Nay I have ſeen my ſelf in a proteſtant Church Moſes himſelf painted on the walls with glittering hornes on his head and a pair of law tables in his hand. But it may be Law makers do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emp themſelves: at leaſt ſome Proteſtants may interpret as they ſeem to do, that Moſes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad to make the figure of Jeſus Chriſt but not his own. No man in England ſcruples to have any of theſe eikons, no not the Doctor himſelf, notwithſtanding this law of Moſes ſo expreſly contrary to them all; no man doubts to ſet any painter or graver on work. And yet muſt ſtill this law be caſt in the teeth of Catholicks as tranſgreſſors of it. For Gods ſake why is St. Mary Magdalen in her penitential weeds upon her knees, with beads in her hand, and eyes all blubbered and ſwoln with tears, more againſt the law of Moſes; than one of our delicate Paragons of beauty, in her ſhining dreſs, lips of coral and ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling eyes. <hi>O but Catholicks worſhip them.</hi> Sir
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64186:21"/>this word in the ſence and meaning of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants is as great a falſhood as was ever ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by man. For Catholicks neither have nor can have any other relative eſteem of any picture, than what they have to the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential works they repreſent, or to the worth and piety of the perſons. And an abſolute eſteem of the picture, this is meaſured out only by the Materials, and artifice of the painter; according to which one picture ſhall be worth five hundred pounds, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repreſenting the ſame thing, not worth five ſhillings. And can we believe that our proteſtant young Gentlemen have no vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at all to our beauties ſet thus in their Majeſty, nor no kind of affections riſing in their hearts towards them? Yea ten to one more of ill affections, and, god wot greater, then any good ones we can have to our cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us in our way of piety. And the difference indeed is only this, that our reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and affection is towards holy perſons, and unto an imitation of their piety, hope, patience, conſtancy, and charity: Their's to a concupiſcence of fleſh and eyes. This and nothing but this if truth may be ſpoken, makes them ſo wrathful and furious againſt our Catholick pictures. Satan hates Jeſus Chriſt and therefore inflames them to tear down his memories and repreſentations: but he loves pride of life; and thoſe portractures
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64186:21"/>muſt ſtand that advance this. He is pleaſed with that which feeds concupiſcence of eyes: and concupiſcence of fleſh brings him in the diſciples which Jeſus Chriſt loſes.</p>
               <p>Moſes did forbid Jews who were travelling with him towards Paleſtine an idolatrous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to make to <hi>themſelves,</hi> that is to ſay on their own heads, without warrant of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, or in imitation of the pagan rites, any of the idolatrous images there and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where to be met withal, or any ſimilitude at all, leaſt ſeduced thereby, they leave their own God and religion to cleave unto falſe gods and idolatry. This law of Moſes and purpoſe of the law is ſo clear, that he muſt be obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blind who ſees it not. And what does this concern our holy Catholick figures of St. Paul for example or Chriſt crucified, more than Proteſtant figures of young Lords and fine Ladies; ſave that the one moves us to the love of mortification, prayer, patience, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, the other allures us from it; the one confirms Religion, the other weakens it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our holy pictures are allowed by the Church, the others forbidden. And this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the onely aim of Moſes, when he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the people to make to <hi>themſelves</hi> any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven images whatſoever; to <hi>themſelves,</hi> that is on their own fancies and upon their own authority: For ſuch onely were unlawful, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64186:22"/>not thoſe they were commanded by juſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and allowed to make. See, ſaith God by Moſes, I have called and named Beſaleel, and <hi>I</hi> have filled h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m with the ſpirit of wiſdom and underſtanding and all knowledge of all manner of workmanſhip, to deviſe cunning works to work in gold and ſilver and braſs, and in cutting of ſtones and in graving of wood, to work all manner of workmanſhip. And I have appointed Aholiab with him; and in the hearts of all the wiſe I have put wiſdom, that they make all that I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. And by virtue whereof the ſaid men and others after them wove and graved pomgranets and lilies, and placed Cherubs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Propitiatory, between which graven Cherubims God himſelf gave out his Oracles to Moſes: as he did alſo heal the people by the figure of a Serpent which Moſes comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ſet up. So that here is a vaſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt figures graven and ſet up by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and thoſe which people make to themſelves. The one is commanded, the other forbidden. Aarons Calf of gold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the people, but Moſes his Serpent of braſs healed them. Theſe things are not now ſaid afreſh. They have been told to Miniſters over and again, but they are never the better for it. Indeed they love not to hear of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſpoils their ſport.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:64186:22"/>
               <p>I add yet withal, over and above what is yet ſaid, that neither that law of Moſes, nor any of his Ten Commandments, nor any other of his precepts either ceremonial judicial or moral, does any way oblige Chriſtians at all, as it comes from Moſes, who is not our Law-maker or maſter, but ruler and leader of the Jews. Nor do we Chriſtians believe that theft, adultery, homicide or blaſphemy, is a ſin becauſe Moſes forbad it, but becauſe we have receiv'd from Jeſus our own Legiſlator who juſtified Moſes law and ratified it in all the ſaid particulars, that ſo it is. And it is here to be obſerved that one of the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn laws contained in thoſe two tables, that I mean, which ordains the ſeventh day to be kept holy day, unto which Moſes adjoyns an irrefragable and unchangeable reaſon, namely becauſe God reſted that day when he made this viſible world, beginning his work ſaith Moſes on the ſunday wherein he created light, and the friday following finiſhing the whole; even this law of his moſt ſolemn and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely urged by Moſes, is annulled and abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated amongſt all Chriſtians even from the beginning of Chriſtianity, for want of ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it from our Lord and Maſter Jeſus who is our Law-maker and Prince. And the ſame thing do I ſay of this his preſent law about figures, images and repreſentations of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64186:23"/>things by ſculpture or pencil, which was only of temporal concernment to the then preſent Jews againſt the danger of idols which then filled the earth, and as meer a ceremonial law as the other, and equally concerning a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of worſhip. If our own Prelates whom Chriſt our Lord inſtituted to overſee his flock ſhould for reaſons beſt known to themſelves take from us thoſe little ſmall helps we have by the images of ſome of our Anceſtors, Martyrs, Apoſtles, Virgins, Confeſſors, then would we be without them, and yet not think our ſelves to loſe one jot of our Religion for that. But we will not forfeit them for any law made by Moſes, except it be eſtabliſhed and ratified by our own law-maker or his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates watching over us under our Lord unto our good, if Moſes ſhould have made any law againſt them, which indeed he did not, but onely againſt heathen Idols. And if any one ſhould endeavour to have our Chriſtian repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations to be aboliſhed becauſe he thinks and believes that Moſes forbad them, then is that man ſay I, bound to obſerve all the whole Law of Moſes, as it is literally expreſſed by him, even to the leaſt apex or iota thereof. For the authority of a Legiſlator being the ſame in all h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s whole law, muſt oblige equally in all its parts: and the diſtinction then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween judicial, moral, and ceremonial law, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64186:23"/>nothing; ſeeing that Moſes his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are equally peremptory, and preſs as ſtrongly in the one as in the other. This is no imaginary opinion of mine own, but what reaſon and the Spirit of God moved St. Paul to aver as ſtoutly in the caſe of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is another of Moſes Laws, as I do here. I teſtifie to every man, ſaith he, who is circumciſed, that he is bound to keep the whole law. And this muſt needs be true, moſt certainly true: for by obſerving circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion becauſe it was commanded by Moſes, he ſubjects himſelf to the law and authority of Moſes as his Prince and Legiſlator; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently is bound to obſerve him equally in all things which he commands with the ſame authority and will to be obeyed, which is no leſs then all his whole law. And curſed is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, who is under the law and continueth not in all things which are written in the book of the law to fulfil them. Although then it ſhould be granted that Moſes by his law prohibited all kind of figures and repreſentations, even thoſe uſed by Chriſtians, which he did not, yet if our Lord ratified it not, it does not touch us at all. And that he did not renew or ratifie it, is ſufficiently clear to Proteſtants, becauſe no ſuch law of his is found among the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts: and unto Catholicks no leſs, becauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64186:24"/>there is neither Goſpel nor Tradition for it. And if all men would ſeparate themſelves from prejudice, which blinds and hardens them in their conceits, they might eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that neither Chriſts immediate Diſciples nor any Chriſtians that ſucceeded them after our Lords departure, would have either fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or hated the figure of our Lords counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, if by chance they would have met with it. But if any one notwithſtanding, fully perſwaded that Moſes made a law againſt all ſort of images and repreſentations, ſhould upon that authority of his aboliſh ours, he is bound alſo upon the ſame authority to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice an Ox, and obſerve all the whole law in all and every particular, under the penalty of ſin.</p>
               <p>Since therefore by the order of God and Moſes many graven things were made; repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations and ſimilitudes both in Heaven and Earth notwithſtanding the ſaid law; as the Serpent of braſs (which muſt either be made by melting or graving) pomegranates, lilies and various ſuch-like things both graven in ſtone and interwoven in ſilks, Cherubins or Angels in the Propitiatory, even in Moſes time and afterwards more fully and plentifully in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple; it is not rationally to be doubted, but that this law of his was intended onely to keep thoſe people cloſe and conſtant
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64186:24"/>to their own God and to their own Religion, which was inconſiſtent with the idols of the Nations; and not for any purpoſe of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob, either out of their chamber hangings or ours. I know the Jews do urge this Precept of Moſes very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly againſt Chriſtians ever ſince Jeſus Chriſt our Lord was rejected by them, whoſe image and figure they cannot abide to ſee. But we muſt have patience with all men.</p>
               <p>§ 9. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith he, <hi>grounded this law of his upon a reaſon unchangable, namely that Gods infinite and incomprehenſible Deity cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented.</hi> O profound invention! This is ſuch a law and ground of a law, as was never before thought of. The ground and reaſon of making a law muſt be this, an impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of breaking it. They muſt not make any repreſentations of God, becauſe God cannot be repreſented. And the ſame motive or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will be equally proper for all the reſt of the Commandments: <hi>They muſt keep the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day of the week a holy day.</hi> The reaſon and motive; becauſe there is not an eighth day to keep holy and ſanctifie. <hi>They muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their Parents.</hi> The ground and reaſon of this; becauſe none of the whole Camp had any Fathers or Mothers alive to diſhonour. <hi>They muſt not kill.</hi> The motive and reaſon is; becauſe they were all ſhot-free, and ſo firmly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64186:25"/>inchanted that none could hurt them. <hi>They muſt not commit adultery.</hi> The ground and reaſon is; becauſe there was never a woman in the camp, which any man though provok'd with the higheſt luſt could peſſibly come near or touch with a pair of tongues. <hi>They muſt not ſteal.</hi> The great cauſe thereof is, that there is noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng at all in the Camp for any man to take away. Thus the Doctor imagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to forbid any repreſentations of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God cannot be repreſented. And ſuch another diſcreet mounſieur was he who ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly commanded his bowyer not to make him any ſhafts at all of a piggs ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le: and he gravel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gave him the reaſon for it, becauſe quoth he of a piggs tail no ſhaft can be made. Truth is, Moſes never thought of any ſuch law, nor any ſuch reaſon of it much leſs; but provided for the ſecurity of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews religion, that it might remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable and firm in the mids of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nations round about them who worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed falſe Gods and idols: as Moſes very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently interprets himſelf and all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets after him. Therefore ſaith God by Moſes, thou ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lt have no other Gods but me, thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, as the Gentills do, nor worſhip them. For I am a jealous God and will have no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termingling of devilliſh idolatry with my
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64186:25"/>ſervice; And all the reaſon given by Moſes is gods jealouſie not induring any divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip but his own. This is the very truth and all the truth of this buſineſs, which this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor would turn another way, thereby to make Moſes ſeem as ſimple a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as himſelf. And thoſe idols forbidden by Moſes did ſo involve an oppoſition to the true God and his divine worſhip, that people could not poſſibly betake themſelves to one, but they muſt leave the other. Therefore did Moſes forbid both other Gods beſides their own one God, and all idols together: which was by antient Chriſtians very rationally and wiſely reckoned all one and the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: whereof no leſs a man, then St. Auſtin himſelf is witneſs. But the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of Abraham Iſaac and J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cob could bring no ſuch danger with them. And that is our care, for we are not in danger of looſing the faith of Jeſus Chriſt by keeping the image of him our crucified Lord among us; or forſaking the communion of Saints, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their portraictures before our eyes. We ſhould <hi>ipſo ſacto</hi> renounce our Lord and all his whole Religion, ſhould we ſet up Moſes his forbidden i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ols and make it our religion to worſhip them as heathens did. But we are heartened incouraged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in our Chriſtian Religion by looking
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64186:26"/>on the faces of ſo many our glorious Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, holy Anchorets, and Hermits, pious Virgins and Confeſſours, who profeſt this our Religion before us, bravely triumphing by the power of Chriſts love and divine faith, over ſins allurements, and deaths uglieſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; though incompaſſed themſelves with the like paſſions and infirmities we are our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lves invironed round about. And when we are entred into a Church amongſt ſo many of our worthy predeceſſors, we compoſe our ſelves more heartily to our devotion then otherwiſe we ſhould do, in imitation of them; remembring now that we are come up to Mount Sion, to the City of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, to celeſtial Jeruſalem, and ſociety of Angels, to the Church of Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians conſcript in the Heavens. to God the Judge of all, to the Spirits of juſt men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, to Jeſus the mediator of a new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to the aſperſion of blood ſpeaking better things then Abel.</p>
               <p>§ 10. <hi>The Heathens,</hi> ſaith he <hi>did ill in their idoll worſhip, and yet the wiſer ſort among them teſtifie that they did not hold them to be Gods but worſhiped God in them.</hi> Our acute di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne having now by his fine wit ſo clarified Moſes law, that it might not ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Idolaters as our vulgar painters; he now begins ſo to purifie idolaters practice
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64186:26"/>too, that they may ſeem but in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with our Catholick and beſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. And who would not give his penny to hear him act and ſpeak. The heathens all in general are ſo excuſed in their idolatry, Aaron in his act of apoſtacy, and Jeroboam in his great ſin; that they are all and each of them no otherwiſe faulty then the Church of Rome in his books. Thus doth Mr. Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet convert idolatrous Nations, while he ſits dreaming in his cloſet. Here he dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes and there he exaggerates, here he blacks with his pen and there he whitens; and then he cryes out all is one, all of the ſame meaſure, all of the ſame colour. And truly I believe the great Gyant Goliah and little David might thus be made equal, if the Gyant were beheaded and cut off by the knees, on one ſide; and David on the other ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de, ſet upon a high pair of ſtilts. While Catholicks are made to do what they do not, and heathens not to do what they do, on a ſuppoſal that all this is true, there can be no great difference Let us then hear him what he tells us of Heathens in general. <hi>The wiſer ſort among them, teſtifie</hi> quoth he, <hi>that they worſhiped not the idols as gods but worſhiped God in them.</hi> O very good? Thus the wiſer ſort among the heathens ſay. But firſt who are theſe wiſer ſort? It behooved him to let
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64186:27"/>us know this. But yet for his own pocket-rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he does not. But 2ly what ſays he himſelf to it? O that is needleſs: for his reader will underſtand well enough what he ought to think, when ſuch a Doctor as Stillingfleet tells him what the wiſer ſort have thought. No body would think with fools, but with the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſort alwayes. And his whole diſcourſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds on this ſuppoſed knowledge of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſort and according to it concludes. We cannot therefore doubt of his mind. But have we no wiſe ſort of antient beleevers who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved among the heathens, to teſtifie unto us what the heathens did? Have we no Apoſtles and Prophets to hearken to, no renowned and infallible perſons to inform us? Surely we have, and thoſe ſo many, that we need not have recourſe either unto perſons unknown amongſt the heathens for their teſtimony, or to Mr. Sillingfleet the ingenious tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fler. He tells us <hi>that the heathens did not worſhip their Idols as Gods, but worſhiped God in them.</hi> But our Apoſtles and Prophets tell us contrary things. Hear Moſes ſpeak, who lived among the thickeſt of the Heathens, To whom did they ſacrifice, O Moſes, whom did the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens worſhip? <hi>Imm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laverunt Demoniis &amp; non Deo, Deut.</hi> 32. They worſhiped not God but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, they ſacrificed to devils ſaith he, and not to God. The Nations change their gods, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64186:27"/>indeed they are no Gods, ſaith Jeremy ch. 2. but my people have changed their glory unto an Idol. Baruch another Prophet brings in his teſtimony chap. 4. You have provoked him who made you, ſaith he, even the eternal God, ſacrificing to Devils and not to God. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pſalmiſt he tells us no leſs peremptorily, That they immolated their Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Devils, and ſacrificed to the idols of Canaan, Pſ. 105. and that all the gods of the Heathens are Devils, Pſ. 95. Saint Paul our own Chriſtian Doctor is bold, and expreſly, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies both againſt Stillingfleet and his wiſer heathens; That the things which Centiles immolated they ſacrificed to Devils and not to God, 1 Cor. 10. And yet after all this our Doctor is not aſhamed to juſtifie thoſe his clyents the heathens. <hi>They did not worſhip their idolls</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for Gods, but worſhiped God in them.</hi> And whom ſhall we here believe? Moſes, Jeremy, Baruch, David, St. Paul and all our Chriſtian Doctors, or Stillingfleet rather and his wifer heathens unknown to himſelf? They ſacrificed to devils and not to God; they changed their glory into an Idol: they irritated the eternal God, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molating to devils and not to God; they ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed their ſons and daughters to devils, not to God. Thus ſpeak our Prophets and Apoſtles. But Mr. Sillingfleet affirms, they ſacrificed to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64186:28"/>God, they imolated to God, they worſhiped god and not devils, they worſhiped not the idols but God in them. But I diſcern well enough the cauſe of his miſtake. Becauſe they abſtracted the general notion of God, and applied it, each one to his own idols; therefore he thinks he may ſay they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God in them. But this is a groſs miſtake. For to worſhip God in a thing and to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a thing for God who is no God, are two very differing caſes. Chriſtians worſhip God in Chriſt, and they do well; heathens who worſhiped their Idols for God did ill. Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well our late Uſurper after he had murd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our good King and ſet the Crown upon his own head, would have taken it well, if his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d him they honoured him for their King; but not, if they had ſaid they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the King in him. The firſt word had ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his ears as a grateful ſlattery, the other as treaſon to himſelf. To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſtract the Deity and apply it to another ſubject unto whom it does not belong, is as far as we are able to behead the true God and ſet h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Crown upon the ſhoulders of uſurping devils. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the true real Deity cannot be removed, either by the pleaſure of the Uſurper or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiper, therefore are theſe idols devi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and falſe Gods. God cannot be worſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ped in them becauſe he is not in them; and if they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64186:28"/>be worſhiped as Gods it is Idolatry; or elſe there is no ſuch thing as idolatry upon earth</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aaron,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>made the golden calf, not to reduce the people unto heathen idolatry, but for an embleme of the good Angel who was to go before them.</hi> Here is another excuſe of Aaron his ſmall fault; which drove Moſes his brother and Prince into a great a paſſion of wrath as perhaps he ever felt: even ſo prevalent a grief and anger, that it daſhed in pieces the very rables of the Law he had in his hands; though he was by the teſtimony of holy writ the mildeſt of men: and all this it ſeems for an embleme: And why that emb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em? ſince they had ſuch an emblem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the pillar of cloud by day and fire by night; which was a more ſignificant emblem of the angel who went before them, then any calf of gold could be. The holy Prophets teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fie of thoſe people and Aaron, that in Moſes abſence this figure was melted and founded by them to be ſet up in place of the God, who had hitherto conducted them w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th Moſes now as they thought vaniſhed, out of Egypt into Arabia; and to lead them on the reſt of their way, as their ſupream conduct, after the manner of Egyptian Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. They made a ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f in Horeb and adored the figure, they changed their glory into the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64186:29"/>likeneſs of a Calf eating nay and forgot their God, Pſal. 125. Now if they forgat their own God, and ſlighted him, and caſt him from them, and changed his glory into a calf, and worſhiped the very figure: then muſt that ſculptil or ſtatue be now accepted for their God. The like teſtimony gives St. Sephen, Act. 7. They made ſaith he, a calf in thoſe dayes and offered ſacrifice unto the Idol, and made themſelves merry in the works of their own hands. What can this import, but that they had now altered their religion, renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their former God, and made to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a new one after the manner of Egypt. It is pitty Mr. Stillingfleet had not been with Aaron; his confidence would have pleaded for him a little more handſomly then he did for himſelf. But the excuſe perhaps being hypocritical and falſe would have more offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Moſes, then his former fault. Aaron knew well enough what he had done. And although he ſomewhat minced his fault, yet would he not tell a lye. I caſt a little mettal into the fire, ſaith he to Moſes, and there came out this calf, The Doctor adds two pretty reaſons, why neither he nor the people, could ever think of declining then to any heathen idolatry, Firſt <hi>becauſe they had no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of doing ſo.</hi> As though the very abſence of Moſes, whom they had long expected and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64186:29"/>now thought loſt, were not pretence enough, unto ſome leading men in the Camp to raiſe a ſedition and thereby force Aaron to make them ſuch idols, as they were acquainted with in Egypt. It is well enough known, that by the contagion of thoſe leading men, the Camp was ever and anon in ſuch like tumult and ready diſpoſition to apoſtacy. His ſecond reaſon is, <hi>becauſe no intimation is made that they ſell into heathen idolatry.</hi> What intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is given thereof by the Prophet and St. Stephen he takes it ſeems for no inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation at all. <hi>When they fell,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>into heathen idolatry, mention is made of their Gods, as Baal Peor, Moloch, Remphan; but here Aaron is ſaid to make a feaſt to the Lord:</hi> As though there were not Egyptian idols as well as Syrian; and Oſiris and Iſis, as well as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loch and Remphan. And a feaſt made in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this their new God and religion, might well be ſaid <hi>a feaſt to the Lord.</hi> It was a policy in Aaron, thus to ſpeak, that the common people might not ſuddainly diſcern the alteration. And we may eaſily believe that the leading men, who brought him by perſwaſion and force unto this apoſtacy, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted the ſaid ſtratagem; firſt to get the people more univerſally on their ſide without commotion: and then to put ſomething into their mouths for to ſay to Moſes, if he ſhould
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64186:30"/>chance to come upon them ſuddainly and take them beyond expectation in the fact. For that it was a meer pretence of policy is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by this; that they gave to Moſes no ſuch account of any feaſt made unto their antient true God; and ſecondly becauſe their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Leaders had no purpoſe to make any, for they had now forgot and put away their own true God and caſt him out of their mind, as holy text ſpeaks, <hi>obliti ſunt Dei ſui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Calves ſet up by Jeroboam in Dan and Bethel, were only to keep the people from going up to Jeruſalem and not to bring them to any idolatry of the heathens.</hi> Here is another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for Jeroboam and his peccadillo. Who would not take Mr. Stillingfleet to be a very charitable man, who can cover ſuch a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſins? and yet is it all no other but a ſecret prodigious malice againſt Catholicks, who muſt bear the more and hear the worſe for it. <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſaith he <hi>did not alter the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip, or give any occaſion of idolatry:</hi> No, no. He only kept the people, ſaith he from going up to Jeruſalem, whither they uſed once a year to reſort. And this could be no ſuch great matter; ſince they had the ſame ſervice, the ſame ſacrifice and adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at home. But why then is Jeroboam char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with idolatry in holy Scripture, as one that had done evil above all that went before
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64186:30"/>him, and made h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m other gods and molten images to provoke God to anger, and to caſt his own God behind his back, 1 Reg. 14 <hi>O, ho, thence we conclude</hi> ſaith our Doctor <hi>that an image ſet up for gods honour is idolatry; as it is amongſt papiſts.</hi> And is not this a pretty nimble leiger demaine of a ſlight man. Firſt who taught him that <hi>Papiſts ſet up images for Gods honour? I</hi> have learned amongſt them that they are ſet up for our incouragement and imitation, and for an honourable memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their holy Martyrs and Apoſtles. But what ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our can one of thoſe images be to God? none at all I think, except indirectly, becauſe God is the bleſſed author of all good, whence the ſaid Apoſtles &amp; Martyrs received their ſtrength and grace. Secondly where does this confident man find, that <hi>Jeroboam ſet up his images for Gods honour? Even no where at all.</hi> His own boldneſs is ſo ſtrong in him, that he ſayes what he liſts without any ground or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion at all any where, either among ſacred writers or prophane. Thirdly whence doth he ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her his negative word, <hi>that Jeroboam acted none of the heathen idolatry, nor brought the people to it?</hi> Even from his own confident brain whence he has the other, expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the teſtimony of holy writ which ſpeaks, as it were paſſionatly and very empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically of his notorious idolatry, wherein he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64186:31"/>did evil above all that were before him, wherein he made him other gods and molten images, to provoke God to anger, and caſt his own God behind his back. Can he be Juſtly charged with all this, only becauſe he kept the Iſraelites from going up to Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and made them do thoſe devotions at home which they were wont to do in that mother Citty. Can only change of place ſuffice for the criminous imputation of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where is the ſame adoration, ſame rites, ſame ſacrifice, ſame Prieſts, and ſame God. Is it poſſible that the ſame ſervice and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer-book read by Miniſters of the ſame kind in London and Highgate, be Gods ſervice in one place, and idolatry in the other, all other things agreing but only the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of place? No indeed, it is not poſſible it ſhould be ſo. But it is very poſſible it ſhould be ſaid ſo. Mr. Stillingfleet here ſpeaks it, and ſpeaks it ſtoutly, on his own head, even againſt all Divine authority and upright reaſon. People may ſin againſt eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical obedience indeed, by not coming up to their parochial Church when they are commanded. But they cannot, only upon that ground, be charged with idolatry, or making ſtrange gods, or caſting their own God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind their back. He muſt be a very paſſionate Prelate, and extreamly unjuſt and ſinfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64186:31"/>who laies that imputation upon peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, upon no other ground or motive then that one circumſtantial neglect of place. And yet holy Scripture ſeveral times thus charges Jeroboam; and puts ſuch a blot upon his ſcutcheon both for his own idolatry, and that into which he induced all the people, that he is ſeldom or never mentioned without his black ſirname; <hi>Jeroboam who made Iſrael to ſin.</hi> If it were true at leaſt, as Mr. Stilling-fleet here ſpeaks, that Jeroboam and Iſraels ſin were only a circumſtance of place, and that they and he did in their own tribes but what was done in Jeruſalem, then muſt it needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that there were in the Temple of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem ſuch like repreſentations, as thoſe calves ſet up by Jeroboam in Dan and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel, and indeed the very ſame with them. And thence we may gather for our learning, if this be all true, an axiom of great truth and concernment; namely, that one and the ſame piece of worſhip which pleaſes God in the Catholick Church, is an abomination to him in the waies of hereſie and ſchiſme. The very ſame thing which in Jeruſalem and the tribe of Judah were called Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims; in Samaria and all the reſt of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el apoſtatiſed from them, was but a calf.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:64186:32"/>
               <p>§ 11. <hi>Charles the great a noble Emperour cauſed Books to be ſet forth againſt the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of Nice where images had been eſtabliſhed, called Carolin Books, and aſſembled alſo a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at Frankford<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein both the ſaid Nicen Council was condemned, and all their reaſons for images confuted,</hi> &amp;c. That there were both in the Councill of Frankford and Nice too, ſome Catholick Prelates who propounded difficulties againſt images cannot be denied. For when ever any Councill meets together about any affair, they diſpute <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth for and againſt it; that the Prelates having all things ſet before their Eyes that can be ſaid on both ſides, might be the better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to determine. So doubtleſs it was done by the Apoſtles themſelves in their great Councill held in Jeruſalem about Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where <hi>inquiſitio magna facta eſt,</hi> great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, diſputation, and examination was made about it. All this is certain enough. But yet, that either in Frankford or any where elſe, were made after this their diſpute any final or concluſive declaration againſt the uſe of images amongſt Chriſtians; or that Charles the Emperour ſhould either write books or cauſe any to be written, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt images or the Council o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nice where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they had been then eſtabliſhed; or ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that Council of Frankford to withſtand
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64186:32"/>that other of Nice unanimouſly concluded by the Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates and confirmed by the general Paſtour; this is a thing ſo apparently falſe and fictitious, that there needs no more but the knowledge of thoſe very perſons and times to prove it ſo. Charles the Great was one that adored the Roman Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was himſelf a Member, above all Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours that ever was before or ſince his time. The Council of Frankford, wherein were little leſs then three hundred Catholick Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, was peaceably concluded, and no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion followed upon it; which muſt needs have riſen, if they had condemned another Council lately celebrated and confirmed by all paſtoral authority. Nor was that Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Councill ever annulled or any way cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured either by P. Adrian or any after him. Add to this, that the ſaid Councill was both begun and finiſhed under the ſame Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian, and his Legates Theophilact and Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus, who had preſided lately in the ſaid Nicen Council, where the lawful uſe of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges was eſtabliſhed. It cannot poſſibly be imagined that the ſame Pope and Preſidenes ſhould conclude in Frankford quite contrary to what they ordered in Nice but ſeven or eight years before. It is alſo certain, that the ſaid Council of Frankford, was ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and aſſembled, not about images only as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64186:33"/>the Doctor imagines, but about the queſtion of our Lord Chriſt his filiation, as all antient hiſtories teſtifie, againſt Foelix and Elipand two Spaniſh Biſhops, and Claudius Taurinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, who teaching that our Lord is rather to be called an adoptive than natural Son of God, raiſed much commotion in Spain and France: and this novelty of theirs was firſt condemned at Ratisbone, and afterwards at Frankford. For Foelix after his firſt condemnation, repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Emperour Charles his Court who then wintered at Rheginum; and there ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the Prelates, was ſent thence to the preſence of Pope Adrian, where in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral of St. Peter he revok'd his Errour. Elipand hearing of his ſubmiſſion grew more violent, and by his books both regained Foelix again, and diſturbed all Germany, as he had France and Spain before. And now to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the infection, the Pope and Charles the Emperour agreed to bring together a conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Aſſembly of Prelates in Frankford, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in preſided Theophylact and Stephanus, who had lately concluded the ſecond Council of Nice. Whence it clearly appears that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Stillingfleet quite miſtakes the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Now if the ſame Pope and his very ſelf-ſame Legates preſided firſt in the Nicen Council, and then in Frankford, as the Doctor acknowledges, we may rationally
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64186:33"/>enough conclude, that the Nicen decrees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout images, lately finiſhed in the Eaſt, were made known to the Weſt by their acceptation and promulgation at Frankford, where the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of filiation was decided: For this is indeed very true. But no way can we think that the ſame Preſidents would now undo, what they had done a little before. And that this is indeed the whole truth in this buſineſs, may be yet confirmed by the authority of the Council of Senon kept not long after, which in their 14. decree thus ſpeaks, <hi>Carolus mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Francorum Rex Chriſtianisſimus in Franco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum furdenſi conventu ejuſdem erroris iconoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorum ſuppreſſit inſaniam quam inſeliciſſimus quidam Fae'ix in Gallias &amp; Germanias invexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> By this teſtimony it appears, that Felix over and above his capital errour about Chriſt our Lords adoption, was an iconoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus too or adverſary of images, and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Frankford for both his errours: which is not unlikely by the teſtimony of Platina <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Paulus Emilius: For Platina in the life of Pope Adrian, <hi>Biennio poſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylactus &amp; Stephanus Epiſcopi inſignes Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani nomine, Francorum &amp; Germanorum Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum habuerunt, in qua &amp; Synodus quam ſepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Graeci appellabant, &amp; haereſis Feliciana de tollendis imaginibus abrogata eſt.</hi> And P. Emilius
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64186:34"/>in his ſecond book <hi>de geſtis Francorum</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Councill of Frankford, <hi>Et ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginibus,</hi> ſaith he <hi>ſuns honor reſtitutus eſt.</hi> The like may be proved out of Blondus, Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus and other hiſtorians. So that all theſe things rightly conſidered and put together, will ſufficiently convince his relation of the Frankford Councill to be fictitious and groundieſs. If the Councill were aſſembled by the Agreement of the Pope and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, then not of the Emperour againſt the Pope. If to ſuppreſs Elipand, Claudius, and Felix; then not the Nicen Prelates. If un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Pope and Preſidents which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided lately in Nice, then not againſt any thing determined and concluded in Nice. If upon the motive of Elipands errour againſt our Lords filiation; then was not an image the principal occaſion of it. If Felix were there condemned for his oppoſition to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges then were not images condemned. If Charles the great, one of the devouteſt to the Roman Church that ever raigned, ſo much ſwaied in that Councill, then would he not ſuffer the Roman Church to be there affronted and cenſured. If an upright Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, he would not in ſpiritual affairs gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay the Prince of Prelates, who had ſo lately ſet his hand and ſeale to Nicen defiinitions. In a word if Charles the Great called that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64186:34"/>Council at Frankford, as the Doctor affirms, then without all doubt was that ratified there, which was eſtabliſhed at Nice a little before. For Charles was as much a Roman Catholick as either Stephen and Theophilact, or the Pope himſelf, and knew as well as any man, what obedience is due to the definitions of a Council rightly conſummated and confirmed, as that of Nice was. Binius the great Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of the Councils proves at large, that all this ſtory of the Carolin books and Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Synod aſſembled againſt that of Nice, is a groundleſs fiction. And ſo do Alanus, Surius, Vaſquez, and ſeveral other Doctors. And they are all amazed, whence the rumour ſhould ariſe, and by whom, and in what age or time. But I cannot wonder much at it, ſince I heard lately of a French Gentleman, who affirms and ſhows in a Book of his, that the Engliſh never conquered France, nor ever gave them any one overthrow in battle. And when he was told by a neighbour, of this his notorious falſhood; O, quoth he, my book two hundred years hence, may paſs for an authority as good as any that ſpeak other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. And ſo I think there may poſſibly be ſuch impious men, who out of their preſent malice may furniſh out a lie to infect poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in after times. But he muſt be an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable wicked man who can do ſuch a deed.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:64186:35"/>
               <p>§. 12. <hi>Primitive Chriſtians never uſed any images, as the learned of the Church of Rome acknowledge.</hi> He had done well to let us kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w who are theſe le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rned of the Church of Rome. But he will not do us that favour. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e muſt ſtill take his word for the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the learned ſort always. Nay we muſt bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eve too, that he is ever on the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſorts ſide. It is indeed unlikely that fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of thoſe holy perſons, who firſt ſpread our Chriſtianity in the world, and made it good both by their lives and death, ſhould be frequent in prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tive times. Firſt, becauſe thoſe ſame figures, although they be honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able memories both of their perſons and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, unto whoſe zeal and goodneſs we are ſo much indebted; yet are they not ſo neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requiſite unto any ſuch perpoſe, but that the Church can be without them. Secondly, becauſe primitive Chriſtians had not amongſt them any ſuch plenty of Artiſts, as we have now a days to make them. Thirdly, becauſe Pagans would have miſ-interpreted the end and meaning of ſuch figures, as this our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor does in the midſt of day-light. But that in thoſe primitive times there was never any Chriſtian ſo ill affected towards thoſe pious repreſentations as is Mr. Still. appears ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently by the teſtimony of thoſe ancient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, who mention incidentally the cuſtoms <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:64186:35"/>ſo thoſe primitive times; eſpecially about the figure of the Croſs, which they made conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually on the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r fore-head and breaſts, as a preſervative againſt evil, and kept it all over their houſes, particularly in their Bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and cloſets, either framed in wood or ſtone, or painted in colours. There be not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the deluge of time which ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows up all things, ſome monuments yet left among us of the reſpect which thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans then bore both to the reliques and figures of their Saints. The very chair of St. James the Apoſtle and firſt Biſhop of Jeruſalem, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius in the ſeventh book of his hiſtory at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts, that it was had in great eſteem and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in all times, even to his own days. Accordingly S. Clement in his ſix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h book of apoſtolical conſtitutions gives this general teſtimony of that kind of piety in thoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The very relicks, ſaith he, of Saints now living with God are not without their veneration. Some remainds there be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of an apoſtolical Council at Antioch, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of S. Pamphilus and Origen, wherein caution is given both againſt the Jews malice and Gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le idols, by oppoſing the images of Jeſus and his holy fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lowers againſt them both: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:64186:36"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ignati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s alſo that worthy apoſtolical Prelate, the third from St. Peter the Apoſtle in the chair at Antioch, thus ſignally ſpeaks of the ſign of the croſs in his epiſtle to Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c. The Prince of this world, ſaith he, rejoices when any one denies the Croſs: for he knows the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the croſs to be his own ruin: this is the Standard againſt his power, which ſo often as he either ſees or hears it ſpoken of. he ſhakes and trembles: thus ſpeaks that glorious Prelate. The above named Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius teſtifies alſo in the ſame book of his hiſtory, that he ſaw even in his time the brazen Statue of our Lord Jeſus, which was ſet up in Paneada in Paleſtin, unto his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by the woman cured by him of the blood flix; ſo notable for miracles, that they were ſpoke of all the world over. This ſtatue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Lord when Julian the apoſtate cauſed it to be thrown down, and his own to be ſet up in place thereof, a ſtrange ſodain fire from heaven conſumed the ſtatue of Julian, as Zozomenus in his fiſt book witneſſes. And of the ſame bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en ſtatue of Chriſt our Lord write alſo
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64186:36"/>Theophilact, Damaſcenus and ſeveral others. And here we may take notice by the way, that charity &amp; devotion ſet up ſtatues to our Lord, but apoſtaſy &amp; malice pulls them down. And whether Dr. Stillingfleet, who buſies himſelf ſo much to caſt down the images of Jeſus our Lord and his holy followers, would refuſe to have his own ſet up for his great pains, either in Guildhall or Cheapſide, he knows beſt himſelf. Truly if that were done, I do not believe that any of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours or Countreymen would take him then for a calf of Bethel. Of the Images of the virgin Mary made by St. Luke there is much fame amongſt the antient writers, in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Theodorus, Simeon Metaphraſtes and Nicephorus: The laſt of which does alſo atteſt in his ſecond book, that the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious relick was carried up and down the whole habitable world of Chriſtians, who looked upon it with a moſt greedy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied devotion. The ſame Nicephorus adds moreover, how Conſtantius the Son of Conſtantine tranſlated the rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cks of St. Luke from Thebes, of St Andrew from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaia, and of St. Timothy from Epheſus, unto Conſtantinople, with a vaſt concourſe and joy of Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtian people: and there with all honour and reverential reſpect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhrined them in a cathedral Church dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64186:37"/>to the Apoſtles. Of the image alſo of Chriſt our Lord imprinted by himſelf in a handkercher applied to his own face and ſent to King Abagarus who requeſted his picture, write Evagrius, Metaphraſtes and others. Of another image of Jeſus Chriſt made by Nicodemus, which being ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly crucified by the Jews wrought many wonderous mirac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, we have a ſolemn teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Athanaſius cited in the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth action of the ſeventh great Synod. And all this teſtifies that Chriſtians in primitive times were affected towards holy pictures and relicks as Catholicks are at this day: at leaſt not ſuch haters and vilifiers of them as is Dr. Stillingfleet. Nor can I conceive how any of the learned in the Church of Rome ſhould be ignorant of theſe things. Nay the very Church of England, which this Doctor pretends to defend, hath lately put the images of the Apoſtles and Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Saints into their common-prayer-book and Primers printed by authority. So that if the Doctor had opened his eyes, he might have ſeen clear enough, that all this talk of his is now unſeaſonable, however it might have paſſed well enough in the beginning of the furious reformation: when they pulled down all ſacred figures, and ſuffered none to be ſet up either ſacred or common.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64186:37"/>When husbands broke their wives pictures, and wives their husbands, leaſt they ſhould give ill example to St. Peter and Paul, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage any of the twelve Apoſtles to creep up again upon their walls. When children in obedience and duty to their parents, ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon their effigies, ſaid as they were taught to ſay, I renounce the devil and all his works. When all the people fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cked together in all places to tear down Churches and Chappels, and private oratories in houſes, with a Now boys, we are free men, let us eat, drink and play, for to morrow we ſhall dye. No more duty of any our daily prayers, no more faſting, no more vows, no more troubleſome adoration upon our knees, no more pining meditations, no more pennance, no more reſtitution, no more prieſt, no more altar, no more croſs or holy rood, no more Peter and Paul to be ſeen, no more languiſhing memories of Saints, no more obedience to the erring Church, no more ſelf-examination, no more conſcience ſcruples, &amp;c. Thoſe times indeed were mad enough. But now people, as newly awaked from wine, begin to be wiſer and look more ſoberly about them. Even Denmark and Holland conſider now in cold blood the many ſad miſchiefs they acted in hot: nor is our own Countrey wholly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64186:38"/>ignorant of the irreparable ruins of thoſe mad times. However, our Doctor will not have his ſport ſpoiled, nor yet his game ſtopt. Punchienella, though Bartholmew fair be ended, may be acted ſtill either in Lincolns Infields or Chairing croſs or any where elſe, both now and then and ſeven years hence. It will be ſtill new to ſome body. He may alſo know that King James a wiſe and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prince in the year 1617. gave order that the pictures of Saints ſhould be ſet up in his Chappel of Holy-wood houſe in Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, as Spotswood atteſts in his hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Church of Scotland. And he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant that ſeveral times order and command has been given to Proteſtant people by our Engliſh Biſhops, that they bow and do reverence at the name of Jeſus, when its ſpoken or read in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. Now the name of Jeſus and figure of Jeſus is all one thing; the one of them repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to the ear, what the other does to the eye. All this he might have conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But his tongue is hot, and he muſt ſpeak although it be againſt himſelf, and the very Church he juſtifies, as much as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church he arraignes. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed his whole diſcourſe is ſo frivouſly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and ſubtilely fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>volous, that no Church needs much to heed what he ſayes. This
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64186:38"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> know and am c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tain of, that although he ſhould be confuted at large and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ever by any Catholick Writer, yet ſhall we be never the nearer to any quietneſs and peace. For the next man that wants a rich benefice, will if he have but this mans confidence, collect another book of popiſh idolatry out of this book of Dr. Still. as he gather'd this of his out of Henry Moore, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lor and ſundry others his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; not heeding at all any anſwer that has been given by former Catholicks to the talk, any more than Dr. Stillingfleet does here. They will ever write, one out of another, and never regard what has been ſaid to any one of them in defence of that which they oppoſe, abecedarian ſcriblers. Nor can there be any end, ſo long as there is a biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick or fat benefice to hope for: and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick hands ſo tied up, that they can print no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unto their own juſtification without inſuperable difficulties and hazard.</p>
               <p>I have read in <hi>London</hi> the Defiances of one Fencer to another, both of them in print. Who accordingly do meet in Bear-garden without any controul, there to baſte one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther luſtily for the peoples plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure. And it would be a paſtime <hi>I</hi> think equally delightful, not leſs profitable, and ſomewhat more civil, to ſee two men reaſon down one another.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64186:39"/>We poor men ſhould eſteem it a great favour to us, if our adverſary might read his charge and we our defence, even in Bear-garden. Since neither in Churches, Halls, Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or Schools are we permitted to ſpeak; or print any thing to ſpeak for us. And Doctor Stillingfleet who hath made his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance already, may which he hath not yet done, appoint the day. Not men and fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers onely, but bulls and bears, cocks and dogs, all are permitted to defend themſelves when they are invaded, but onely we poor old Chriſtians whoſe Religion hath bleſſed our Land fifteen hundred years. As if it were agreed on all hands that we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be rightly underſtood.</p>
               <p>Mr. H. Thorndike a grave Divine and and learned Doctor in our preſent Engliſh Church both affirms and ſtrongly proves in his book called <hi>Juſt weights and meaſures,</hi> that Roman Catholicks are idolaters no way: adding alſo, That they who ſeparate from the Church of Rome as Idolaters, are thereby ſchiſmaticks before God. Thus ſpeaks that learned man, the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aenix of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, who only dares to be honeſt. And the mere authority of this eminent Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant may ſuffice to evacuate all the ſophiſtry of this whole chapter of this Doctors book:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64186:39"/>as alſo of that which follows in the next place about our holy Hoſt and Saints.</p>
               <p>Now Sir, I muſt bid you farewel. And that you may not think me either idle or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective of my duty and reſpects to you, pray give me leave to tell you, that what you ſee here printed but now, was written and ready for the Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in Auguſt laſt. And before October ended <hi>I</hi> had finiſhed all my work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Dr. Stillingfleets Book, ſuch-like familiar Commentaries, as theſe upon his firſt chapter be. But in all theſe ſix months <hi>I</hi> could get no more printed for you either at home or abroad, than this poor fifth part of the whole, after my many travels, vexations, expences and dangers. Such obſtructions are made about the Preſſes, and ſo many vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences offered here continually, far above any uſed ſince we were born, that <hi>I</hi> can ſee no poſſibility for any whole book of ours to ſhoot that gulf, be our cauſe never ſo inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and good. Nay, they will here print our catholick books themſelves, as if they were their own, as Thomas a Kempis, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nada, Parſons Reſolutions, Drexellius, and the like. But if we be taken printing them, the PRESS is broken, PRINTER puniſhed, and we, if we be found, in danger of our lives. And therefore I beſeech you, Sir, be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64186:40"/>content with thus much, or rather this little<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The reſt you ſhall have in written hand. In the mean time let Dr. Still. triumph and crow as he pleaſes. He is made and has made him. ſelf ſure enough. Although he hath defied the whole catholick world and all that know of it, having ſomething to ſay, are both wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ready, yet will no man come forth into the open field againſt him, becauſe they cannot. He thinks himſelf wiſe no doubt; wiſer than millions of men: and may do ſo ſtill. For my part, Sir, I find him as wiſe as one man; and no more. Farewel.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:64186:40"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
